[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers
on the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hello this is justin baier for software
engineering radio and today i'm speaking
with thomas graf about ebpf
thomas is a co-founder of psyllium and
the cto and co-founder of isovalene the
company behind silly
previously thomas worked at red hat and
cisco as a linux kernel developer on the
linux kernel and various other open
source projects
welcome to the show thomas thanks a lot
for having me justin yeah of course
so just to start off the show i want to
discuss
a little bit of a baseline before we
dive into the ebpf
i want to talk a little bit about how
the linux kernel is structured so
from a high level can you kind of
discuss you know
how does my user space program interact
with the linux kernel and a little bit
about the internal structure of the
kernel
sure um the kernel is
what typically sits between an
application and hardware
or appliances and
it is there to abstract the hardware
away so applications don't have to care
about what hardware
are your regular only and that could be
real hardware or could be virtualized
virtualized hardware
and the kernel is fundamentally event
driven so it will
only do something if you ask it to do
something right
it's not magically doing something there
are maybe some timer related things that
are happening but generally
there are system calls that are
happening from the applications for
example hey i want to open a file
or hey i want to do an a tcp network
connection
or there is hardware telling the kernel
i have something to read
or i have a network packet that has just
come in you need to do something about
it so
the kernel is there to act on those
events and to connect
hardware with applications to for
example allow an application
to open a tcp connection or to store a
file or to read from a file
and so on okay so it's event driven
we're leveraging sys calls
from the user space into kernel space to
drive those events
so we're going to dive a little bit into
this into where ebpf fits in that but
before we get there
i just want to talk a little bit about
how are changes actually made to the
kernel
so if we specifically talk about the
linux kernel which we do in the in the
context of ebpf
it is an open source community it's
hundreds or thousands of
kernel kernel engineers or kernel
developers who will
make source code modifications it's
i would i'll call it relatively old
school so it's still using mailing lists
it's not using slack it's not using
github yet it's
it's using git or git was actually came
out of the the kernel development
movement
so you have a hundreds of thousands of
people that are making
code changes that then run on millions
and millions of devices from
high-end servers to really small
embedded devices
which leads to this interesting scenario
that
have many many many different interests
and they all have to agree on that a
particular change makes sense for all of
them
so all of this creates this very unique
very very interesting
kind of group of people that are that
all have
similar goal but they're not all caring
about the exact same
thing yeah so it's almost like that
debate you get when you have the 500
distributions of linux of which one do i
pick
you're still at the kernel level trying
to summarize all of those
higher level specific like ubuntu
changes or
deviant changes or arch changes and
you're trying to kind of boil that down
to core
essence and say okay but this is the
actual functionality we need
in the kernel exactly exactly but the
huge benefit is
if you have something in the kernel it's
available
everywhere right linux is everywhere
these days so if you manage to get
functionality in
it means you have this available on any
smartphone that is linux based on any
linux server
on most home appliances that linux space
so
the the gain you get from something
integrated into linux kernel is huge
obviously so then kind of diving into
ebpf
how did that actually get introduced
into the linux kernel this is very
interesting
uh ebpf kind of origins from bpf
which is the the older more natural form
of it berkeley packet filter which is
is older than i am so it's very very old
and it is the original packet filter
from the bsd days it's
a small coding languages that call a
small coding language that allow to
write filters to for example if you're
on tcp dom to specify
with which packets should actually be
displayed or if you have a raw socket
which packets should be should be
received on a
raw socket so it's something low level
in the kernel that was
used to select a subset of network
packets and ebpf
is the extended version of that and
the motivation for it was that it became
harder and harder to find consensus
among
all among all of the linus kernel
engineers because a certain change may
make sense for
a google or a facebook or one of the
other very big companies utilizing
linux for high scale environments but it
may not make sense for for example
embedded systems
and this led to a motivation or to a
discussion is
kind of under the way of can we make the
linux kernel programmable and this is
where ebps draw it
okay so just to kind of go a little bit
back
when we're talking about packet
filtering
what actually is that because i know
some of our listeners may not be super
familiar with that
lower level network stuff yeah so packet
filtering
is done on multiple occasions the most
obvious one is
is for example a firewall right if you
if you want a security firewall you need
to be able to do packet filtering
to decide should i allow this packet or
should i not allow for this packet
uh the example that most people are
probably probably aware of is iptables
where
you have a rule such as i want to allow
ssh
and i want to drop everything else and i
want to allow all of my reply packets
and that's it like a stateful that's a
typical stateful packet filter
but there are other cases as well one is
a one is uh
something i've already mentioned which
is tcp dump you can run tcp dom to
capture network packets on a network
device
and display them for example for network
troubleshooting
in this case you also want to apply a
filter and for example say
oh i only want to see network packets on
port 80
or i only want to see tcp packets with
the syn flax set
and so on that's those are typical
examples of a packet filter
yeah and commonly i here discuss you
know tcp dump underlying something like
wireshark to display the actual captures
and
view the pcap files and all that kind of
stuff exactly exactly tcp dump is kind
of the
the raw form and wireshark is the gui on
top exactly so
you mentioned how evpf is kind of this
programmability in the linux kernel can
we kind of talk about how
ebpf is actually working under the hood
like integrated into it
like how is that actually hooking into
the kernel absolutely
evpf by itself is a bytecode language
which is is restricted but relatively
general purpose so you can write
programs which contain logic the kernel
then provides
a whole set of hook points to which you
can attach those programs
and run them when a certain event
happens and this suits nicely into the
event driven architecture of the linux
kernel so for example you can run a dpf
program
when a network packet is received or
when a network packet is transmitted
or when a system call is being made or
when a tree trace point is passed
or when um when a user space probe
function is called
and so on so the kernel provides a set
of hook points which you can extend and
run a bpf
program and that program can then return
a verdict
to instrument or to indicate to the
colonel what to do with
at that talk how to proceed further okay
and
we are going to dive a little bit into
those discussions about you know what
those hook points are and stuff and we
discuss a little bit later about writing
ebpf programs
but i just kind of want to talk about
what are we talking about with
complexity of ebpf
when we're talking you know time cost
memory cost if i want to write
an ebpf program how much of a hit on my
system am i going to see
so ebpf is specifically designed to be
as
efficient as possible and for that
reason it actually comes with a just in
time compiler
which means that even though you're
loading generic byte code
portable byte code into your linux
kernel but just in time compiler will
compile that and translate that into
whatever your cpu runs so from an
efficiency perspective you're very close
to execution speed
as if you would recompile a kernel evpef
programs are typically not very complex
there's even a complexity limit to
programs because from a kernel
perspective you don't want to allow
users to load programs which might then
stall the kernels
ebpf programs have to be fundamentally
secure and having a
known complexity or an upper complexity
limits
is a key part besides other other
aspects yeah and we'll dive into some of
those restrictions a little bit more
later on i know there's some
restrictions around looping and pointers
and all that kind of stuff
so when you're saying the just-in-time
compiler though are you talking about is
that where llvm kind of fits into that
layer
so there's two layers of compilation
that happen first of all bpf is an
assembly like
language it's uh it's looks very similar
to x86 assembly
and yes you can write the pbpf bytecode
at that level but that's not what you
typically do
you typically use c or a pseudo c
language and then use llvm to compile
sudo c into ppf pipe code
and then the kernel will translate that
again from the
generic pipe code into for example x86
evpf
okay and who's maintaining all of this
stuff within evpf because it sounds like
there's definitely a lot of underlying
functionality that's dependent on
constant maintenance exactly there's
multiple layers that
are stacked on top like if we start from
the very bottom there is
the edpf subsystem in the kernel which
is maintained by daniel borkman and
alexa story voitov
and andrei i sorry andre i completely
forgot i forgot your last name but
three maintainers on on the eppf kernel
side that's what's in the
kernel side uh this is the engine this
is the chit compiler this is the
verifier which we'll talk
later about this are the hook points
everything that runs
in the kernel and then there's a lit ppf
which is also maintained by the kernel
community that's low level
and then on top of that is um various
tool set like for the compiler suite
llvm
and then tools like cilia and bcc ppf
trades which are higher level
tools they're still very much in the
ebpf ecosystem because most users will
not typically write pf programs
themselves they will leverage a tool
that sits on top that provides a
more user-friendly way of actually using
it
yeah and we're going to discuss bpf
trace and some of those other tools when
we start talking about troubleshooting
the programs you're writing at bpf
but i just want to give a couple
examples of some functions
of writing an ebpf program what's going
to motivate me to write one of these
things
rather than just depending on a psyllium
or something like that
i think the vast majority will not like
write ebpf programs i think in bing
eating that was very much the case
a lot of the high leveling tooling did
not exist if you look at the typical use
cases to
leverage bppf it's tracing it's
networking it's uh security
for all of these major use cases a
tooling exists right if you are
if you're looking into profiling and
tracing you will use something like ppf
trace
and only if there is no specific
program in the huge set of the huge
library of existing ebpf programs
only then would you actually go in and
write your own eppf program
the learning curve is definitely
definitely high similar on the let's say
the sec
the system called security side there's
segcomp there's a second ppf
you there's no real reason why you would
go down to dppf layer you want to
benefit from the power of ebpf but
typically you can
you can make full use of it without
actually fully understanding ebpf
so i think unless you're starting or
unless you're looking to start a new
ebpf project
most likely you will start out with some
of the higher level tooling first
yeah so unless you're trying to dive
straight into you know i'm writing xyz
project and i need to do this kind of
interaction with the kernel and the
kernel devs won't accept my
patches you know that's when you might
start looking at
using something like ebpf to do that so
just kind of changing direction a little
bit the other
you know acronym that i hear thrown
around when evpf is discussed is xdp
can you kind of discuss what that is and
how that kind of fits into ebpf
yeah so xcp is the express data plane
and
in a nutshell it's the ability to run a
bpf program
inside of the network driver of linux
and why why would you want to do that
right i think
that sounds a bit it sounds a bit crazy
if you come from the networking role
it's actually not crazy
in the networking world it's several use
cases
quickly evolve around how
how many packets per second can you
handle so for example if you perform
high high performance load balancing
or if you if you perform ddos mitigation
the type of measurement you care about
very quickly is about packets per second
like how many packets per second can you
load balance
what type of ddos attack can i sustain
from a packets per second perspective
and in that context it's actually very
useful to run
as close to the hardware as possible so
you want to be able to do packet
filtering
or load balancing without actually going
through
millions millions of lines of kernel
code first
in that sense xtp comes in and it allows
you to program network logic
incredibly close to the hardware which
means that you pay the least amount of
least amount of overhead before you get
to the bpf program that does the actual
work so it's almost getting
an evpf insert before
drivers or at the same level as a driver
would be getting within the networking
hardware
it's at the same level as a driver but
you still have for example instead of
first of all creating what's called an
skb a socket buffer which is the
generic abstraction of a network packet
inside of a driver every driver will
have its own
view of things it's still very hardware
specific and then the linux kernel has
this abstraction layer on top which
makes everything generic and that is
already pretty costly you do memory
allocations and so on
xdp allows you to run logic before this
before you pay this
this big first cost it means that you
don't have access to a lot of what the
kernel provides
a lot of the for example there's no ip
or tcp or anything like that you're
talking about raw network packets
but if you do load balancing or if you
do ddos mitigation you don't need any of
that
all you want is to to be able to look at
the packet as early as possible and
um either do a load balancing decision
or say i need to drop this packet
because this is part of adidas attack
okay and just kind of diving into let's
say the ddos example a little bit or the
load balancing example a little bit
how am i passing that information into
xdp to say
you know yes these packets with this
signature
need to go away or these packets with
this signature need to be directed
to this ip address or something to that
effect exactly yes this is where
the generic nature of bpf comes in so
bpf consists of the program
aspect which is the actual program
called the logic
and then the second big aspect is bpf
maps those are data structures they can
be hash tables
that can be lpm longest prefix matches
table
and so on like a wide set of
data structures and typically the
configuration of a program is in those
maps so
if you look at for example a ddos
mitigation program
you would typically store the the ip
ranges or the
deciders which you want to drop in an
lpm table and your xtp program will
basically
parse the network header look at the
source ip address
and then see if there is an lpm match in
the lpm table
and if so drop the packet so that's the
program logic is relatively simple
and the actual configuration on what you
want to drop is actually encoded in ebpf
program
which means that if you change if you
need to change what you want to drop
you're not rewriting the program
you're only changing the content of the
bpf map
and this bpf map can be modified both
read and written to from user space as
well so there's a
system call that allows a application
running in user space to take control
over that ebpf program and to end the
eppf map
okay so i could almost have my user
space program running you know ddos
mitigator
that's getting network calls with citer
information from my security
infrastructure
and that's then updating the map
in bpf and then my xdp program
is referring to that bpf map and then
acting based off that
exactly so you have the control of what
we typically call the control plane the
controller
portion is in user space typically
written in something like go or another
high-level language
and the actual data path that needs to
be really fast handling millions and
millions of packets per second
that is in bpf xdp very very low very
low level okay
and you mentioned lpm tables in
passing there i'm assuming you're
talking about longest prefix match
exactly
can you kind of discuss what that is
because i'm not sure how many of our
listeners would be super familiar
with that yeah this is something quite
networking specific and it's the notion
that
if um on the internet you have you have
routing and routing means
routing is the the logic that decides
where network packets need to go
and in order to avoid that every single
device on the internet needs to know
every other device on the
internet there is something called
subnets or routing which means that some
devices will generally know
in which direction the packet need to go
and then the closer you get to the
destination
the more accurate information you have
in order to implement this you have
something like a longest prefix match
which means
it will always match on the the most
accurate the most
exact version of the information you
have so if you know about the
exact destination ip it will match on
that
but you can also add an entry into that
something like an ip 10.0.0
24 which means the last eight bits could
be anything and it will only match on
the first 24 bits
that's the longest prefix matching it's
something very networking specific
yeah so usually here like the simple
example as you kind of mentioned you
know you have that
10.0.0.
and then you have that 10.0.0.0.
you know eight the slash 24 is what's
going to win because it's that
longer prefix it's more defined more
specific
exactly so just kind of moving along
here
you kind of talked about xtp fitting in
at that
you know hardware interface nik level
you know
network interface card and evpf kind of
underlying that
as the logic is there any other use case
where you're going to want to start
using xdp
in combination with ebpf i think the
prominent use cases right now
are ddos mitigation and load balancing
and load balancing primarily what we
would call
north house load balancing that's
typically packets
coming into a data center or into a set
of machines
these type of load plans are typically
exposed to the internet so they're
subject to a lot of traffic
and you typically have a small number of
load balancers and then a
vast number of servers behind those load
balancers
for those xtp is ideal because what you
typically do in the for those low plans
is you receive a packet from the network
card
you do something to the network packet
and then you send it out the same
network
card so you're not actually that you're
not actually delivering it to an
application running on that same server
or on that on the on that
linux machine you all you want to do is
manipulate manipulate the network packet
to do the load balancing so
change some change certain fields in the
network headers and then send it out
again
those are the prime use cases for xtp
but they're definitely others as well
there has been talk about doing early
dmox in xdp
there's definitely cases where you can
do something like encapsulation in xdp
there are cases where i've seen people
build uh
net 46 so the translation from ipv4 into
ipv6 and back
for example for iot a lot of iot iot
devices will only do ipv6
but the actual backend applications are
written in a way that they don't
understand ipv6 and so on
all of those low level network functions
can be can be done at
very high speeds with xtp and when we
talk high speeds that usually also
translates to very low power consumption
per operation so it's not necessarily
millions of packets per second it's also
just watts per packet that sense so if
you have very little compute power
available xtp is very interesting as
well
yes so that's where it almost has that
perfect fit for the iot environment
where
you know if i want to stick x iot device
in someone's refrigerator
i don't want them changing the batteries
every single day because they're
they're not going to buy my product
anymore if that's the case let's kind of
talk about
how we write these programs you know how
i'm writing an ebpf program or an xdp
program
just from a high level what kinds of
libraries can i use to write an ebpf
program for example and then we'll kind
of discuss
about writing xdp programs yeah so
first of all i think the first category
is to not even write an ebpf program but
to just
leverage one of the tools i want to
emphasize that enough because
i think there is a perception that oh i
need to learn about ebpf i think that's
great but
you can leverage all of its powers
without actually having to write
your own program if you want to write
your own program
there's a set of libraries that you can
use starting from like there is
there's a rust implementation so you can
write programs in rost
there are ways of writing ebpf programs
in golang
typically the actual program code is
always
in sudo c so i use always some form of
of c code that is a bit it's kind of a
limited set of c so
you can't do arbitrary cs arbitrary c
you can do function calls by now you can
do what's called bounded loops but you
can you can't loop forever for example
so there's
it's a subset of c that you could use
you write that code and then you
either use llvm or more recently gcc
also has ppf support
and you run it through the compiler and
that will generate you the bytecode
at that point you will load that pipe
code into the kernel using the loader
infrastructure there is lip epf there is
tc there is pcc and a couple of other
loaders this is this is the
code that will take the bpf program and
load it into the kernel
so it will make sure that the dpf
program has the proper elf headers and
all of that to make sure the kernel
actually understands
and then this will load it into in into
the kernel
at that point the kernel will verify it
and
make a judgment whether the program is
safe to run and then either complain
or successfully load the program okay so
that's a lot to unpack there so let's
just kind of take this
like one bit at a time here so first
we're writing our code using some
library so
essentially we're creating some type of
pseudo c and i've also
heard the library for python bcc thrown
around handling a little bit of that
compilation on
automatically for you so then you're
compiling it into bytecode and you're
putting it into an
elf format can you kind of dive into
what that is and why you're putting it
into that format
yes because you need to like one aspect
is just the code itself and then another
aspect is you need metadata around the
program so
you need to understand what ppf map does
this program
use you need to understand how the
program should be loaded so at what hook
point should it be attached to um you
need to understand
who is loading this program and then
more recently also like
ebpf signing so the signature of the vpf
program is also being discussed so that
is
the program itself and then a bunch of
metadata that needs to go along with it
and that needs to be standardized so
kernel and user space need to understand
how this information is encoded so both
both sides can actually understand it
yeah and alpha is usually a common
format
for or a common standardized format in
the linux world for passing these
binaries around
yes so then it's getting
and we're going to discuss those hooks
and trace points and stuff like that a
little bit later
but so then it's getting loaded in so
how is that loading process
actually working so is that something a
kernel syscall that's pulling that in is
there a loader within the kernel that's
doing this
so it's a it's a system call there's the
ppf system call that
you can use to load the program the same
system call is also used to create maps
to attach to maps to
uh to pin maps we can talk about that as
well what that what that is
to access maps to write into maps to
read from apps and so on
but there's one system call that you do
to load the program so you can say here
is my program
this is the elf attach it to
let's say the tc layer that's a traffic
control layer and i want to run this
program
every time a network packet is received
on ethera for example and
and you tell this to colonel the kernel
will take the program verified and
attach it to
to that to that hook point and the
moment it is attached and that the next
network packet that is arrived will flow
through that
through the dbpf program okay so it's
still got that verification layer so can
we kind of talk about what that's doing
what is that checking for how does that
kind of work
and then what kind of feedback is it
giving to you as a developer if
something's wrong
yeah i think a lot of our listeners
might kind of be wondering at this point
why are you going through all of this
why are you just loading a linux kernel
module
the linux kernel was always extendable
and the very big difference between
a linux kernel module and ebpf is safety
ebpf is from design
secure which means that you can't load
arbitrary functions so it may sound like
making the kernel programmable means i
can call into arbitrary kernel functions
that's not true
you can call into what's called ebpf
helpers or helper calls
it's a it's a subset of the functions
that the
the internal kernel api offers but in a
stable manner so even across kernel
versions it will be the same so
it's a the the amount of complexity and
the amount of operations an eppf program
is can do is limited and the verifier
ensures
that this is this is met so a couple of
checks that the verifier does it will
first of all check the overall program
size
so you can't load a 50 megabyte program
into in in into the kernel the kernel
will reject it there is a
agreed on upper limit for ppf programs
and then
the kernel will do verification of every
single
branch that exists in a program so it
will it will calculate all the
possibilities that the program could go
into
and it will make sure that all of those
paths
run to completion so it will ensure that
nothing can loop forever
it will also make sure that nothing is
uninitialized so every single piece of
memory has to be initialized and so on
there's a long list of things that it
will do
to ensure that ebpf program even if it's
harmful
cannot crash the kernel and it cannot
stall the kernel so even if somebody has
access to the pppf system call which
is typically protected by privileges but
even if somebody
loads a malicious program the verifier
will ensure that the kernel can continue
running so that's a huge
major difference between a linux kernel
module and
ebpf okay so it has that almost
implicit benefit of even though it's
event
because it's event driven there's no way
to completely stall the kernel on an
event so
you know if i hook into network traffic
i can't write a program that just does
an infinite loop and
basically takes your entire server down
if i got on it yeah
exactly you can you can still you can
still do things like drop all your ssh
packets and lock yourself out but
you cannot do something like let's just
loop forever and then my kernel will
stall
exactly so you can still shoot yourself
on the foot like everything with linux
but yeah
you can't completely take the system
down
so what is the benefit of this
over a user space program i mean
generally with a user space program i
mean or even
you know a kernel module as you kind of
mentioned the benefits it's
more safe but from a developer
perspective
why am i going to go towards evpf over
writing a kernel module or writing some
user space program to do this
the only occasion where we actually want
to do this if you
need to run it in the linux kernel so
when do you need to run in the linux
kernel
one aspect is you are seeing
everything that the application is doing
so for example
if you want to implement what's called
container runtime security or system
call filtering and restrict
restrict the number of system calls a
particular application can do
you need to run in the linux kernel
because system calls are being made
through the linux current so you need to
run as part of linux kernel
or if you want to get involved into
networking
you either need to do this in the kernel
or you need to do
something like user space networking
where you bring the hardware to user
space
but typically the the main reason why
you want to write an ebpf program is
if you're if the context you need and if
the
the use case you have needs to be solved
in the kernel that's what's
that's what's that's why ebpf is there
it does not make sense to port arbitrary
applications into ebpf
exactly so there's no reason to port my
hello world program into evpf
because you know it works just fine in
user space and it's really
starting to get into that concept of if
you need to start intercepting cis calls
that's when you need to start going into
the kernel
but one other good example is for
example if you want to
to do performance troubleshooting of
your applications right you can
either go on and make modifications to
your application and
for example add trace points and add
print case or printfs
or like linker link in some debugging
library that will do profiling for you
but that requires you to recompile and
restart your application
with ebpf you can do a lot of this for a
already running application because the
kernel is always in a position to
observe what the application is doing
and this is where it gets really
powerful the kernel has access to
observe everything that is going on on
the system and it can
take control over everything that's
going on the system in a completely
transparent transparent manner
without having to change any application
code this is where a lot of the benefit
is coming in
if you look at a lot of the ebpf talks
around for example tracing and profiling
it's about
performance troubleshooting on live
applications in production where you
cannot restart them you cannot run a
debug version of this
but you still need to figure out why
your application is slow you still need
to figure out
your distributed application running on
hundreds of servers what is consuming
cpu like which functions are consuming
how much cpu
typically if you run this on your your
in on your laptop you would
you would link in some debug library or
something that would give this
information you cannot do this for the
application running in production right
this is this is the key benefit of the
kernel it can see and control everything
that's on the system
exactly because you know you can't push
a debug version of
my giant distributed mail client
nobody's gonna like it if all of a
sudden their email has a bunch of error
messages popping up
on the client side it's bad user
experience so just kind of driving back
here
you kind of mentioned you know we've
talked a little bit about bpf maps
so you mentioned pinning maps can we
just kind of
discuss what pinning a map is and why
you're going to do that
so as we mentioned bpf maps contain the
state of the application or
configuration
it's a set of data structures that just
immediately brings up the question
who owns these maps right so
you have the bpf program it's running in
the kernel
but the bpf program can actually access
multiple maps
and the map can be accessed from
multiple bpf programs so the map itself
cannot be owned by the bpf program
you can for example have a program
on the network level and another one on
the system call level and they can
both interact with the same ebpf map
we also said that the ebpa although that
the linux kernel is event driven
and a user space application may not
live forever
which means that it opens up this
difficult question
who owns the ebpf map at what point
is it no longer used and for this
purpose it was decided that we need to
somehow
pin that to the file system so it needs
to have some representation where you
can see
this ppf program exists or this map
exists
and there needs to be some way to
release that resource again so kind of
delete the map
and for this reason there is a bpf file
system and
every bpf map can be represented on the
file
system and you can access it through a
file descriptor
this allows a program that loads cppf
program
or like a user space process loading the
program into the kernel to actually
quit and terminate and then start again
and access the map again so you don't
need to have a process running all the
time in user space
and as soon as that process would
terminate all of your programs would be
gone
all the resources all the programs all
the maps are pinned to the file system
so they will exist even if the user
space process
terminates or crashes or or something
this is why pinning
pinning exists it's also a way for other
programs to discover the maps so you can
have multiple users based processes
and they can discover a map by just
opening the file system
and opening the file basically
yeah so your program's coming up and
it's able to do that you know file
descriptor you're doing an open syscall
on that actual file that's underlying
and
as you kind of said you know and we
might discuss a little bit when we
discuss containers but
you know they're ephemeral they can go
away and disappear and
go everywhere and they still need to be
able to access these things without
getting rid of that file but that brings
up a question
is there any kind of garbage collection
on this how does it know this is no
longer
you know needed anymore no not really
it's it's the the
responsibility of the program loading or
the process loading the program to also
remove it again
in typically ppf programs are a very
crucial part of
the overall system if the ep program
does load balancing or for example
container networking
you want that to continue running under
all circumstances because if
it not being available could have
tremendous uh consequences
so the worry is always that something
some failure and user space could affect
what what the overall system is doing so
there's no automatic garbage collection
it's
it's the it's the responsibility of the
process
uh which loaded the the program to also
remove it again
okay so essentially whatever loaded the
bpf program through the bpf syscall is
also responsible for
unloading the bpf program and cleaning
up any of the mess that it created
yes okay so that also brings up
another question that i have so we've
mentioned throughout like trace points
you know k
probes k trace what are these things
within the kernel
that we're actually hooking it can be
almost
everything actually so it's actually a
very very good question because
the number of hooks that exist are
continuously being extended
they already range from if we start from
top
user space probe so even your regular
applications process is running in user
space you can define a
so called user space probe and say if
this function
inside my application is called then
invoke this eppf program
this is how you can profile your own
user space application
you can do kprobe so for any kernel
function with
a known symbol you can attach a ppf
program when that function is entered
and when it exits for any trace point
and the
linux kernel system or the linux kernel
provides or maintains a a long list of
trace points
stable names to which you can attach to
for example
a network packet is being transmitted on
the ip layer or
block storage access from like the
generic block storage does a read or
does it write and so on
all of those are generic trace points
then it goes all the way into
very very specific scenarios such as tcp
congestion algorithms so you can write
programs that optimize how tcp
congestion algorithm works
or every system call that is being done
you can attach a bpf program too
or xtp as we mentioned like very
networks networking specific
or socket operations so sockets are used
to do network operations of the
application you can attach ebpf programs
too
ebpf is really becoming this very
general purpose
programmer programmability layer and is
making its way into
almost all of the kernel subsystems
there is an ebpf program to do
infrared frequency reprogramming or
something like like
very like very niche right very niche
but it it shows the wide usage of of
eppf
i think in the future it will even go as
far as
code that is currently written by kernel
developers natively and merged into the
linux kernel in the future might be
written
in ebpf because it will be more secure
it might be hard for us to believe but
even kernel developers will make
mistakes even kernel developers will
include box and having a verification
layer that is another safety net
will have huge benefits because any bug
in kernel code will affect millions and
millions of
of of users out there so i think ebpf is
really becoming this
very general uh programming layer for
the linux kernel in general right
we're talking linux kernel uh right now
but i think it will actually make its
way
outside of outside of linux as well we
are we're already seeing early on signs
of this like there's a freebsd port
um there's been tweets from microsoft
about this so i i definitely
bbpf will become much bigger and will
make operating systems in general
programmable yeah because it's almost
providing that safe
abstraction layer within the kernel not
really an abstraction but
a way to hook into the kernel in a more
safe manner than people were doing when
they were writing modules
or like in the windows world when you're
writing you know really low level
drivers that are hooking into it to do
some of these things
you know it gives you a little bit of
verification that you aren't getting
with those other things
it also makes programming easier because
if you
if you write a linux kernel module for
example you are using
internal kernel apis like functions or
libraries that the kernel internally
provides there is no stable guarantees
given by the kernel
kernel community that these functions
have some sort of
api or even api compatibility which
means every kernel version may break
this
so you will have to adjust your kernel
module code for every
for every color reason you might even
have to release it for different kernel
versions and so on
ebpf has this abstraction layer in
between that
yes you can for example call a function
that will get you a random number back
but there is a this this is a stable
function that you call
and even if the backing implementation
changes that the actual helper call that
api will always remain stable
yes so kind of going along that example
you know if
for example the kernel changes how
you're getting a random number and they
change the function name from get random
to get you random
now that's a breaking change for your
module and now you're putting a
nice little if statement in there to
check and see which kernel versions
you're on and whether it's supported or
not
but from an ebpf perspective you can
have just a simple you know
get bpf random and whether it goes to
you random or
debut random or dev random it doesn't
matter because from a developer
perspective you're
getting the same api call between
exactly
for those who have written kernel
modules in the in in the past
kernel module typically is thousands of
preprocessor if conditions if kernel
version acts if kernel version y
and then different code it's a mess
right it's a mess
yeah and it's horrible to maintain
because now you have to
watch the kernel mailing list and you
know almost have a little
regex filter looking for whatever
function names you're using to see
did someone propose a change to this did
someone propose a change to this
and then giving that feedback to say no
don't do this or oh wait i gotta fix my
entire module now and re-release
but kind of going back a little bit
you'd mention the concept of
um hooking anything with a known symbol
in the kernel
i'm not sure how many of our users would
be familiar what does that mean when
you're saying a known symbol
so if you run your kernel typically you
don't have to symbol table available
which means that kernel functions are
are behind arbitrary addresses right
like kernel like memory addresses
and in order to understand where a
function starts or where a function
where
code for a function is located in memory
you need something like a simple table
and the symbol table will map the name
for example
system call write like where is the
implementation for the write system call
and will contain the memory address
where is that code for that system
call in memory and if you have that
simple table available you can basically
say
i want to load an ebp i want to run an
ebpf program
when the system call function for write
is invoked or when it returns
and this is what what kprobs is about
for this to function you need that
simple table
because as a human you don't recognize
the symbol
the symbol or the memory addresses but
you will you will recognize the human
readable function names
yeah and even if you do know the
you know memory address specifically
because you sat there and debugged it
the problem is when you have stuff like
address space layout randomization
turned on which should be turned on in
your kernel and you shouldn't be turning
it off
you still need that symbol layer to do
the symbol table to do the translation
for the address for you
since hard-coded address really doesn't
work anymore exactly
so we've kind of talked about
writing these programs a little bit so
how am i gonna troubleshoot
this program if i'm writing one are
there like tools that i'm gonna use to
do that
yes i think we can speak from our own
experience uh as a maintainer of
psyllium one probably the biggest ebpf
program that currently exists
we invested a lot into a troubleshooting
and debugging layer
and it's fantastic because
we were able to leverage the the tracing
layer of vpf so
one of the prime use cases of vvpf is
tracing and when you do tracing you
typically
you hook into user space applications or
into kernel functions
and then you emit a some event for
example
i um i have observed something or
you want to emit the string or something
and then show that in user space
and for this the so-called perv ring
buffer exists it's a it's a ring buffer
that allows an ebpf program to send
events to user space in a very efficient
manner and for user space to
retrieve those events and for example
print them i mean it's
it's an arbitrary generic ring buffer it
could be messages it could be
it could be really anything we are
specifically using that
to basically bake in debugging so it
means that in the in the code
we can basically print debug messages
anywhere we want them
and then on the fly actually enable
enable this this is very interesting
because of the
the nature of ebp if it's possible to
atomically replace programs
we can even in a production environment
actually enable
data path troubleshooting messages and
like very similar to how a kernel
developer would do debugging with like
print k statements
we can do that but actually without
recompiling kernel without restarting it
so
that allowed us to do a lot of fantastic
troubleshooting when when
when needed because if you run in the
kernel it you can't simply attach a
debugger
it is possible but it's not as easy as
it is for
for for a user space application well
yeah because you're trying to hook into
the underlying operating system and now
when you hook a debugger to things it
messes everything up and gets all weird
yeah and like in a lot of cases you
can't even just sleep and break right if
you are processing a network packet you
can't just
okay let's wait that option does not
exist you would break your kernel
or if you're doing a system well in a
system called you could actually
sleep right that's actually feasible
your
the application during the system call
would then sleep and stall and it would
look like deadlocked or something but
that's it that would actually be okay
but for a lot of the other ebpf program
usages it's not possible to even just
break and stop as a typical debucker
would do
okay and you were kind of mentioning you
know this debug layer and being able to
atomically replace
programs how are you actually doing that
atomic replacement in uvpf
yeah so the the really fantastic
property of evpf is that the program
and its state is separate so if you look
at a
typical application the when you load
the program and if you want to replace
the program of your of your users based
process
you have to restart the entire program
the process and you will
also lose all of its memory you will
lose this stack you will you will lose
like everything like you will start from
scratch with ppf this is different
because the you will also lose the stack
right
because the stack only exists for one in
the invocation of the program
but between invocations of the program
you can replace the program
atomically while the map state prevails
which means you can for example collect
statistics or
maintain a connection tracking table in
bpf or
have firewall rules in the map and then
replace the program with the bpf system
call atomically
while the state still persists which
means you can
you can you can apply hotfixes you can
upgrade your programs
without actually disrupting anything
that's going on
so almost if you had let's say a debug
switch in your control plane
you could say flip this into debug mode
it'll swap out and load the debug
version of your bpf
code and because your map is pinned as
we discussed earlier
that doesn't get thrown away because
that's the responsibility of the program
to clean up
instead now you have this debugging
version but
how does that work with that ring buffer
that you were discussing earlier does
that get cleared
for or is that new for each instance of
a program or does that actually persist
that persists as well a ring buffer is
just another bpf map as well so that the
ring buffer is always there as well
so essentially because that's still
there again as you kind of said you're
not losing anything by swapping it out
to the debug version now
you know the buffer might just fill up a
little more because you have more debug
messages coming out
yeah and if because it's a ring buffer
even if the the bpf program is very
quick and may process
let's say only a couple of thousand
packets per second it may still emit
hundreds of thousands of debug messages
the user space program
doesn't have to be quick enough to read
everything in real time
it can buffer everything in the rim
buffer and then at a later stage read it
because the the user space program may
not actually have
may not be scheduled on the cpu at the
same time as the bpf program is running
so this allows for a kind of a
a single switch that kind of oh i need
debugging now uh maybe for the next 10
packets and then
disable it again because all i need is a
couple of traces to figure out what's
going on in my program
you can even do things like uh only
because you can atopically replace the
program
if you know the failure scenario you can
only enable the debugging if a packet is
arriving
matching that failure that specific
failure failure scenario this is how we
have for example
track down box around ipvc ipv6
extension headers
we would have logic in there that would
only emit the traces
if the if packets of ipv6 extension
headers would be would be received and
so on
it's i've actually been fantastic at
least from a perspective of a linux
current developer where
that's that's kind of our standard right
like from a perspective of a
let's say a java application developer
it's still very difficult to upload to
debug an
ebpf program but compared to kernel
development it's actually
it's actually very handy yeah you know
when you're used to having that user
space you
know apm you know application
performance monitor
reading everything in your code you just
go to a web interface and see run times
for each function
it's a lot easier than trying to write a
program to handle some ring buffers and
maps and all that kind of stuff
so i kind of want to change directions a
little bit here and start talking about
some of the use cases that we have with
ebpf i mean we've discussed a
bunch of them so far you know anything
from you know xtp being used in the
knicks
and even projects like psyllium and some
of the use cases you guys fulfill but
i do want to talk you know as we've
moved into a more containerized world
how do you get
ebpf to understand that concept
of a container that's an interest that's
interesting
because the linux kernel and this may be
a surprise the linux kernel does not
actually know what a container is
the linux kernel understands c groups
name spaces
process boundaries process forking and
so on but it doesn't actually understand
container container uses
all of what i just mentioned to to
create like container isolation or the
concept of a container
so you cannot go on and say colonel
give me give me the memory usage of
container if container idx the kernel
does not know what container idx is
you would need to translate container
idx into the actual c
group id and then ask the kernel okay
this container is using this c
group for memory consumption or for
memory isolation
show me the configuration or something
show me the usage and so on
and this is where ebpf comes in and can
make
the kernel indirectly aware of concepts
like kubernetes
container micro services and so on by
allowing it to for example do
uh packet filtering or system call
filtering
with the awareness of container id
because or containers or parts and so on
by encoding that as part of ebpf
programs that that's making it so
powerful the reason why that's even
needed in the first place is because
typically the time between writing a
kernel feature
and the time by the time it gets
available is multiple years like
it's often five plus years like somebody
writes a kernel feature and then by the
time that kernel release
gets into the hand of users it's just so
long that it's very rare that the kernel
is actually
up to date in terms of use cases the
kernel that you run
right now it's probably not been written
with your current use cases in mind and
evpf programs you can prob
obviously load any program that you want
which means you can bridge that gap
this is what's making it so powerful
yeah so it's giving you that flexibility
that you don't actually get with kernel
development
because of the fact that kernel
development's delayed it takes forever
to get a patch in
and then even once you have that in now
it has to be rolled out to all the
distributions and not everybody's
running the latest version of the kernel
in their distribution and
you know every other what-if scenario
but just kind of circling back so you
mentioned the concept of name spaces c
groups all that kind of stuff and as you
kind of mentioned
probably most software engineers aren't
going to know what that is
they might understand the concept of a
container but they might not know how
that works at the lower
kernel level can you kind of dive into
that a little bit and explain it
sure so i think containers are two
aspects like one is the container image
which i will not cover a lot of the
packaging
shipping the entire dependencies and so
on that's one aspect and then the other
aspect is
the deployment form like how it actually
runs on the system
and the migration or the movement away
from virtual machines as the deployment
or kind of the
the isolation form to a container in
which case
the kernel becomes responsible to
negotiate the resources between
containers because obviously we're
running multiple containers
on a single system which means somebody
needs to be
aware and in charge of for example
making sure that one container cannot
use all of the memory of the entire
system or all of the cpu on the system
or
who ensures that the the networking
of one container like one application
running in a container cannot just
access the other application in another
container on the same system because
from a networking perspective that would
obviously be possible if you don't do
the isolation
for this purpose the concept of
namespaces has been
has been created actually much longer
than containers exist as a concept it's
been
many many many many years and then later
on the concept of c groups have been
introduced as well
it's all about making the littles code
multi-tenant so multiple
multiple applications multiple tenants
can operate a single system
without necessarily trusting each other
and by providing isolation on all levels
cpu memory
uh networking storage file system mounts
users and so on yeah and this is where
that benefit of the kernel almost being
that
chokepoint helps because now it can
filter syscalls that are
accessing these items based on those c
groups and that's where you know you can
start leveraging ebpf to hook into that
but to kind of dive into some examples
here so
how would you roll out ebpf in something
like a microservice environment
you know for things like observability
networking security
i know that's a lot of what psyllium is
actually capable of doing
yes so so suleiman is a networking and
security layer for specifically for
kubernetes cloud native and for
networking
you typically we can use the specific
example of
kubernetes which i guess is the most
most most dominant uh
container platform right now you you
typically come as a so-called cni
plug-in like containing an orchid
interface at that point
you are the the component that is
responsible for
allowing containers to to communicate
with each other like
contain to container and also how to
communicate to the outside world
and how how to allow the outside world
to talk to containers
and in that sense the cni plugin that
actually has a lot of freedom on how to
do this
specifically most cnr plugins will use
so-called virtual ethernet pairs to
create a virtual virtual ethernet cable
basically
between the network namespace of the the
container
and what's called the host namespace so
like there's always like
namespaces and and c groups are almost
always um
like in you know come in the form of a
tree so you have like an init or a
hostname space or a c group and then you
can
go down into multiple levels so you need
to bridge the
the container namespace with the actual
host and then also bridge that
out to the outside world this is what
the cni does and that
that gives the opportunity to attach an
ebpf program
to that virtual ethernet cable so it
sees and controls all of the network
packets that come in and out of a
container
and for the case of of system calls
you would typically attach the ebpf
program
to the c group so all of the system
calls being done
in the concept of that c group which
then is equivalent to
all of the system calls being done in
that container would go through that
ebpf program as well so
you're using the kernel level constructs
which are used to build containers
as a way to integrate into containers
okay and that's almost something like
where falco would almost hook into that
system that's
using that evpf and filtering based on
those c groups and
then looking at the specific sys calls
coming from those specific containers
exactly yes yeah and back on episode 341
i know we discussed a little bit about
container networking and on 290 we
discussed some stuff around docker and
security and
some of this lower level stuff and how
this isolation works
but just to kind of dive into some
specific examples here
with observability you know we've kind
of mentioned tracing
would i hook my ebpf program into some
type of overall like distributed tracing
framework
or is it really just like pod specific
for kubernetes for example both actually
so
in the case of psyllium you offer kind
of
all the way from low level network flow
logs what you would expect from a
typical network
layer all the way into higher level
tracing languages like such as open
tracing
tracing information that you would
typically only expect from the
application levels like understanding of
http calls
cough cut topics grpc calls
and so on dns information like high
level like clearly beyond what you would
typically get from a network
observability platform
but also we can do both and that's the
that's a
really part of the really powerful
aspect of ebpf because
we can combine what we see on the
network level from a packet perspective
but that we can also hook into for
example the socket layer and understand
the data that an application sends or
receives
or even instrument envoy um which is the
the layer four proxy that cilium uses
for some of the http parsing
and get information from that as well
that's that's the
the the true power of it because ebpf
can be used to glue
everything together and then combine all
of that information to probably
provide a very meaningful visibility
layer that's that goes well beyond what
you would
what typically existed so far yes so
you're almost getting that full stack
monitoring capability from an
observability perspective so this would
almost replace or at least supplement
something like putting like an apm
library into my specific code
or you know having all of my engineers
implement
you know open trace this is almost that
i can get this same level of
observability without having to make
every engineer rewrite every piece of
code
yeah absolutely and the real powerful
part here is that
this will work even for applications
that you don't want to change anymore
right
um in a lot of scenarios you don't even
you may not even have access to the
source code so
the option it it's not the decision
whether you want to change
or don't want to change your application
you just don't for some applications you
can't you're running
a proprietary piece of code and you
still want to instrument it or you want
to understand what type of http calls
are going on
what is the latency how long does it
take for a
rest api to respond and maybe you don't
have access to the source because maybe
you cannot add instrumentation code and
this is where ebpf comes in and you can
do this at multiple levels you can
combine the visibility you have at the
network layer and then also instrument
with ebpm for example the http layer of
the application such as the
http goal library and for example add
trace points to figure out how long does
it take to decode and parse an http
header how long did it take
for the application to respond and so on
and combine all of that so you can
answer questions
is the application slow is the network's
low is it tcp
is it like overall cpu on the system you
can correlate
what you see in terms of latency with
for example tcp re-transmission so you
understand whether maybe it's a lossy
network and
this this is the really interesting part
you can combine all of this
which gives you a very compelling
compelling visibility layer like a true
answer
which was just not available for evpf
not because the information did not
exist but simply it was
spread across multiple systems typically
yes so
how does this compare to something like
an istio service mesh
that's an interesting question uh we get
that a lot and
there's a lot of overlapping in kind of
the values we provide like
service mesh psyllium the
the ask or the the promise is to provide
visibility into applications network
service calls and so on a transparent
matter
the implementation is very different
like service mesh or istio typically
uses
what's what's called sidecar proxies um
to inject
uh proxies into the application parts
and to
to extract visibility from there the
outcome is similar you get a transparent
you get a piece of code that
sits in there transparently and can
observe and control like
in the service measure is the case it's
the sidecar it for still limits the ebpf
program
the big difference is that there's
always like an
a latency and an overall performance
overhead between sidecar and
and ebpf and we could talk a long time
about about that
but i think the even more fundamental
difference is that
service mesh typically relies on
for a lot of the functionality to kind
of have end-to-end visibility you need
to have the side car proxies on both
sides for example mutual tls will not
work if you
if you don't have sidecars on both sides
uh with a lot of what psyllium is doing
because it's integrating on the kernel
level it does not require
to have this it doesn't need does not
require to manage both sides
you can easily do for example http
latency tracing
while only running on one side of the of
the connection so
only for example the client is somewhere
else and you're not controlling the
client you can still measure http
latencies for example
but overall i think you can get the same
or very similar information from both
systems
yeah it's and we've discussed i think
back in episode 361
more on the seo service mess
specifically but as you kind of
mentioned it's all dependent on
the proxy and the sidecar being able to
work on both ends of the connection and
you get some of those benefits like
you know mutual tls and some of those
other security benefits but as you
mentioned if you don't control the
client
you're missing half the connections so
there's not really as much value there
and you're also adding like a latency
overhead for
all of these connection calls whereas
with ebpf i mean as you mentioned
earlier
it's near execution time
exactly and i think the other thing to
mention here is that
the sidecar will only see like layers
layer four and up right like
you don't have and you have any
visibility what's going on in the kernel
so you cannot correlate this information
with for example network visibility or
network layer information or tcp
retransmissions and so on
you cannot answer the question whether
it's network or application
all you see is kind of sidecar and up
there's also just a complexity overhead
i think
the the real benefit from like the ebpf
model is that from a user perspective
nothing changes right like the kernel is
to most people is
it's basically already this huge big
black box and you're adding pro
programs into the kernel and it will do
address or kind of extract visibilities
you're not changing anything from
how it looks to the end to the end user
whereas in the service mesh
model you're definitely changing in way
i mean the site
is visible to application developers
it's running as as part of the
kubernetes pod which is typically owned
by the application team so it's
definitely
visible to some extent and you're
changing
you're changing how the network flows or
happening and so it's definitely a
a more involved architectural change
and that's and that's a i don't want to
bash
service mesh too much i think a lot of
what service mesh is bringing is
actually
absolutely fantastic i'm not 100 in
agreement with the current cycle
implementation model
i think what we will see longer term is
that the
the control plane and the the the user
interfaces of service mesh
will continue to exist and i think we'll
see
more and more of the side car or the
more and more of the service mesh data
plane to be implemented by something
like cilium or ebpf where
you still get the same high level
benefits but you will have a more
efficient
data plane implementation yes so you'll
essentially start to see
as i can imagine like with the mutual
tls like that might still exist within
that service mesh layer
you know some of the you know pot
authentication might still live within
that control plane service mesh but when
we start talking about like lower level
observability and application tracing
and network tracing
that's going to start to maybe migrate
into the closer to the kernel world
where
you know you're preserving kind of the
black box layer between
you know the kernel and user space
absolutely i think there's even a like a
more fundamental difference here which
is
or like another very fundamental
interesting point which is
salim can for example do policy what's
called policy driven tls termination so
you can
you can terminate the tls connection on
behalf of the application you can also
do this with service mesh there's a
difference here though that
if you throw this as part of a sidecar
you are
within the bounds of the part within the
parts within the bounds of what's owned
by the application so if that
application gets compromised in some way
whatever the sidecar is doing is
also gets compromised in the case of
psyllium and with evpf we can do this
outside of the part so it's outside of
the control of the application
which is really interesting if you are
running untrusted workloads so if you
cannot fully trust
the workloads that you're running in
your clusters but you still need for
example tls termination or you want
token injection and want to use certain
and want to
force certain services to use
certificates or keys in order to access
an external service
with ebpf we can do this outside of the
pod
which means you can you can run fully
untrusted for clouds and don't have to
expose any secrets or certificates to
them
okay so when you get the proprietary
black box from your vendor you can still
you know inject some of the security
that you want in there exactly yeah
that's that's a that's the common use
case
so i just want to wrap up the show now
and start closing this out
so what are some resources you would
direct people to
if they want to learn more about evpf
they want to learn more about xtp
you know writing this code something
like psyllium and where that fits in
yes so i think the best starting point
is a website called ebpf.org
it's a community-owned website that we
have launched a couple of months ago
it will give you an overview of ebpf
basically everything we covered today
and also list all of the projects that
exist in the ebpf ecosystem so if you're
interested in tracing what are the
projects that exist around tracing if
you want system call
security what projects exist if you need
container networking what are the
projects that exist and so on
we also have a eppf slack community uh
ebpf
dot io slack that link is also an ebpfio
hundreds of ebpf developers or other
people learning about eb or
with an intent to learn about vpf in our
slack community
helping each other out and then we've
also covered psyllium
you can find more information about
sodium on cilium.io a source of great
talks is uh is the ebpf summit which we
hosted a couple of weeks back
dozens of really amazing talks um
about open source projects in ebpf
project in the ebpf space
you can also find that on ebpfio that's
definitely there's i think
great intro level talks to
low level ebpf verifier internals like
like really anything that that your
heart could could ever wish for in the
eppf
space yeah i was watching some of those
summit talks there's actually a really
good keynote
um from the recent one on just some
basics of writing a basic bpf
ebpf program and that might be good for
listeners if they want to start getting
exposed to what the code actually looks
like
so what other stuff are you working on
now any additional research in the area
there's so much going on in ebpf right
now that i think it would be unfair to
mention just a couple
i think in general we're seeing the
space is literally exploding right now
like
um we're seeing huge investments into
linux security modules which is the the
overall runtime security layer that the
kernel provides
google is heavily investing in there i
think that's super interesting
we're seeing ebpf obviously in the
overall security space in the visibility
space in the networking space
uh we're seeing more and more tracing
tools come up there was i think pixie
labs just launched a couple of weeks
back as well with
really interesting topics there's just a
lot going on right now
it's really hard to to even uh keep
track of what's going on i think it's
the promises is huge and a lot of people
are just starting to realize the full
potential of it and we'll we'll see a
ton of stuff getting created by ebpf
but again i think it won't be that a lot
of people will
will natively use ebpf like evpf has
been designed for kernel developers and
it will
remain like that but a lot of the higher
level projects that are written
on top of it will be very very
interesting to a lot of people
yeah so it'll be like most things at
open source i'm going to start taking
someone's already implemented project
and then tweaking it as i need to for my
environment
all right well thomas thank you for
coming on the show and discussing bpf
and xdp and how we can leverage them for
observability networking and security
i will definitely put links to those
sites that you mentioned and some of the
resources i used for research
uh on this topic awesome that this was
great that's not for having me
justin this is justin baier for software
engineering radio
thank you for listening thanks for
listening to sc radio an educational
program brought to you by ieee software
magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening